Now that the core burger builder functionality is finished for now and as I said, we will revisit this
Artk temel ekirdek Bergere Boulder ilevsellii bittiine ve sylediim gibi bunu bu derste daha sonra bu
later in this course to also submit this to a server, to have multiple pages in this application and
sunucudaki bu uygulamada birden ok sayfaya sahip olmak iin gndermek zere tekrar gzden
much more,
geireceiz.
before we move towards these steps, let's finish this app by adding a bar and a sideDrawer.
DS saplamasna doru hareket etmeden nce bir bar ve bir taraf ekleyerek tatl bitirelim.
This of course is crucial because later once we add multiple pages, we need to have some way of navigating
Tabii ki bu ok nemlidir, nk daha sonra birden fazla sayfa eklediimizde orada gezinmenin bir yolunu bulmamz
there
gerekir.
and every application should probably have a toolbar,
Ve her uygulamann muhtemelen bir ara ubuu olmaldr.
it makes it look better.
Daha iyi grnmesini salar.
So let's close the components, the burger folder in the components folder and layout in UI so that
imdi bileenlerin klasrndeki Bergere klasrndeki bileenleri kapatalm ve ykle ve buradan temiz bir
we have a clean working project here
alma projemiz var, bunu izole edelim.
and let's add a new folder in the components folder over there now.
Ve u an orada bileen klasrne yeni bir klasr ekleyelim.
I'll call it navigation because I want to store all navigation related components like the toolbar, like
Buraya navigasyon diyeceim nk yan ekmece gibi ara ubuu gibi tm gezinme ile
the side drawer in there and the toolbar is actually with what I'll start.
ilgili bileenleri ve ara ubuunu aslnda ne balayacamla birlikte depolamak istiyorum.
So in navigation, let me add a new folder toolbar, and in there
Dolaysyla, navigasyonda bana yeni bir klasr ara ubuu eklememe izin verin.
unsurprisingly, let's add a toolbar.js file.
artc olmayan bir ekilde ara ubuu nokta js dosyas ekleyelim.
Now that toolbar.js file, how should this look like, how should the toolbar look like? It's actually going
js dosyas, ara ubuu nasl aslnda ilevsel bir bileen olacak gibi grneceine nasl emin grnyor.
to be a functional component
imdi, ara ubuu
because it don't need to manage any state in there.
nk oradaki herhangi bir devleti ynetmek zorunda deilsiniz.
I expect to get some props there and then as you know, we're outputting some jsx. For that reason,
Baz sahne takmlarn oraya getirmeyi umuyoruz ve o zaman bu nedenle baz GSX ktklarn biliyorsun.
let's also import react from react here and let's export this toolbar function here as the default
imdi re-act'ten yeniden aktarmay buraya aktaralm ve bu ara ubuu ilevini buraya bu dosyann varsaylan
of this file.
olarak da aktaralm.
How shall the toolbar then look like from jsx perspective?
Ara ubuu nasl kabua GSX perspektifinden bakt.
I want to have a wrapping header element because the toolbar is the header of my web application and inside
Web uygulamamn ara ubuu ISDE stbilgisi ve ieride sonunda bir ift e olmasn istiyorum
there, I want to have a couple of elements in the end,
nk kaydrma bir stbilgi esi istiyorum.
I want to have some button which opens the side drawer and we're going to remove this dummy placeholder
Yan ekmeceyi aan bir dmenin olmasn istiyorum ve burada bu kukla yerini kaldrp daha
here and replace it with real button later on
sonra gerek dme ile deitirelim.
but for now, let's keep this div here.
Fakat imdilik bu dev'i burada tutalm.
So I want to have that,
l olmak istiyorum.
then I also want to have a div which contains my logo and will have to add this and thereafter, I want
Sonra da logomu ieren bir div sahibi olmak istiyorum ve bunu eklemek istiyorum ve oraya navigasyon
to have a nav item which contains my navigation links.
balantlarm ieren bir naff kalemi istiyorum.
So basically this will contain some unordered list with all the links and I'll remove the unordered list
brakyor bylece u anda yer tutucular bu eleri kendi bileenleri ile deitirecek bir logo bileeni.
for now and just leave the ...placeholder here. So all these are placeholders right now, we'll
kullanabileceimiz bir men bileenini ve hepimizin tekrar kullanmak istediimiz navigasyon eleri bileenlerini yeniden kullanabilir.
replace these elements with their own components, a logo component which we can reuse, a menu component
Yani temel olarak bu, tm balantlar ieren baz srasz liste ierecek ve hepsi imdi
which we could use and a navigation items component which we also want to reuse
listenin erefini kaldrd ve u sralar DOT DOT DOT yer tutucusunu burada
since we also have a side drawer for mobile layouts since we might not always have all navigation items
Mobil dzenleri iin hepimizin bir yan ekmecesi olacamzdan, ara ubuundaki tm gezinme elerine
in the toolbar,
sahip olmayabiliriz.
sometimes you want to shift them to the side drawer and therefore having a reusable component for these
Bazen bunlar yan ekmeceye kaydrmak ve bu nedenle bu eler iin tekrar kullanlabilir
items makes a lot of sense.
bir bileene sahip olmak ok mantkl.
Before creating any subcomponents, let's create that base toolbar though
Herhangi bir alt bileen oluturmadan nce, yine de bu temel ara ubuunu oluturalm.
and of course this toolbar will also need some styling.
Ve tabii ki bu ara ubuu baz stillere ihtiya duyacak.
So for that, I'll add my toolbar.css file
Bunun iin bunun iin ara ubuum nokta C'sini aadaki gibi ekleyeceim.
here too. In there,
urada iki tane var.
I'll create a toolbar css class which we can later import because we're using css modules, of
Bir ara ubuu oluturacam nk dersleri daha sonra ie aktarabildiimiz snf olarak gryorum nk
course and I want to have a toolbar which has a height of 56px and the width of 100%.
C'yi elbette modller olarak kullanyoruz ve 56 piksel yksekliinde ve yzde 100 genilie sahip bir ara ubuu istiyorum.
Now the goal here is to develop this application mobile first,
imdi burada ama, bu uygulamay mobil ilk nce gelitirmektir.
so I'll first of all set up the toolbar settings here for mobile devices and then, we'll have a look
Her eyden nce iki ayar ve ayarlar burada mobil cihazlar iin ayarladktan sonra bir gz atalm.
later in this module here where we need to adjust it to also look good on desktop devices.
Bu modln ilerleyen ksmlarnda, masast cihazlarda iyi grnmesi iin hepsini ayarlamamz gerekir.
Though for the toolbar, most settings should actually work for both desktop and mobile, which is why
imdi bunu kaydrp stte otursak daima stte olacak ekilde dzeltme pozisyonundayz. .
I start with the toolbar. So let's now set the position to fix so that it's always at the top even
Ara ubuu iin ou ayar aslnda hem masastnde hem de daha iyi
if we scroll and for it to sit on the top,
alyor olmal, bu nedenle ara ubuuyla baladm,
of course I need to set top 0 and left 0.
Elbette st 0' ayarlamal ve 0' terk etmeliyim.
I then give the toolbar a background color,
Ara ubuunu arka plan rengi deilim.
and here I already picked a nice brownish color,
Ve burada zaten ho kahverengimsi bir renk ald.
#703B09,
7 0 3 be 0 9.
that should look really nice. I'll set the display to flex so that all the items in the toolbar are aligned
sra konumlandrma eleridir, nk ara ubuundaki tm elerin birbirine hizalanmas iin ekran esnek hale
next to each other because the default directional flexbox is row, positioning elements next to each
getirecek ekilde ayarlanmas gerekten gzel grnmelidir. flex bloklar ile ilgili makaleler.
other even if they are block elements and check out some articles about flexbox
Varsaylan ynl esneklik kutusu, blok eleriyse bile birbirinin yanndaki
if this concept is totally new to you. Flexbox has this justify content property which defines how the
Bu konsept tamamen yeniyse, flex kutusu, ara ubuu tarafndan nasl sarlm elemanlar
elements which are wrapped by the toolbar
tanmlayan content zelliini hakl karmak zorundadr.
class item here should be spread out
Son e yaylmal.
and here, I want to use space between so that the available space is filled with the elements inside this
Ve burada, sonsuza kadar bu ara ubuu esinin iindekilerle birlikte mavi yolun boluunu
toolbar element in the end and that they automatically keep some distance from each other.
dolduracak ve birbirlerinden biraz mesafe brakacak ekilde boluk kullanmak istiyorum.
Align-items then determines how they should be aligned
Ardndan, bir satr esi nasl hizalandrlacan belirler.
vertically and there I want to center elements.
Biz yasaltk ve iki ana unsur var.
Finally I'll add some padding,
Sonunda biraz dolgu ekleyeceim.
the padding here should be zero from top and bottom
Burada dolgu, stten ve alttan sfr olmal.
but 20px from left and right and then I'll set up box-sizing and set this to border box to make sure
Ama soldan saa doru 20 piksel ve ardndan da kutu boyutlandrma ve ara ubuunun dolguyla bile doru boyutta
that the toolbar is sized correctly even with the padding.
olduundan emin olmak iin bu kutuyu kenarlk kutusuna ayarlayn.
And finally I need a set index and here will pick 90, important of course,
Ve nihayet bir dizine ihtiyacm var ve kahraman elbette nemli 90 seecek.
this number here has to be lower than the number we picked for the backdrop
Bu numara, arka plan iin setiimiz saydan daha dk olmal.
and there I chose 100
Ve ben 100 setim.
because the backdrop should go above the toolbar, at least
nk zemin en azndan ara ubuunun zerinde olmaldr.
I want to have this behavior here. Now I'll add one more rule in the css file,
Burada bu davran yapmak istiyorum, imdi bir kural daha ekleyeceim ve u ekilde:
I want to control how the nav item is displayed when nested inside a toolbar which it of course will be, there
Nasl kontrol etmek istiyorum D-Nev. e elbette orada olaca bir ubuk iine i ie
I want to set a height of 100% too so that in the navigation, I can then also control the height
grntlenir Ben navigasyonda daha sonra da ara ubuu yksekliine gre yksekliini kontrol edebilirsiniz bylece
relative to the toolbar height and can make sure that the navigation items span the full height of
yzde 100 bir ykseklik ayarlamak istiyorum ve navigasyon eleri bu ara ubuunun tam
this toolbar. With that, that should do it
yksekliini o bor ile rttrecek ekilde geniletti.
for now, let's go back to the toolbar.js
imdilik ara ubuuna dnelim.
file now and let's import our css classes, so I'll simply add import classes from ./toolbar
imdi dyor ve biz de bizimkiler ithal edelim. c. snflandrmas ve Barresi SS'ye ie aktarma snflar ekleyin ve
css and then I'll add this to my header, I'll there add a class name and set this to classes and use that
sonra bunu benim stme ekleyin veya bir snf ad ekleyin ve bu iki snf ayarlayn ve bunu C S S snfn barndrmak iin kullann.
toolbar css class
s snflar olarak basite nokta
we just created
Sadece yarattk.
and as always keep in mind, this import in the end simply imports a couple of strings,
Ve her zaman olduu gibi, bu ithal Hintliler basite birka dizeyi ie aktarrlar.
the dynamically created css class names which we simply adjusted to be scoped to this component and
Dinamik olarak C-s snf adlar olarak oluturuldu ve bu bileen iin ykseltilip ayarland
then, we're assigning the class name which was generated here.
ve sonra burada retilen snf adn atadk.
Now with that, we should have a basic working toolbar,
imdi bununla birlikte, temel bir alma ara ubuuna sahip olmalyz.
now of course we want to use it
Elbette onu kullanmak istiyoruz.
and where shall we add this toolbar then?
Ve o zaman bu ara ubuunu nerede ekleyeceiz.
Now of course you could argue that you want to add it in the burger builder because that is where we want
Elbette Briger Bowlinger' dzenlemek istediinizi iddia edebilirsiniz, nk burada st ksmda bir
to have a toolbar at the top
ara ubuu var istiyoruz.
but in the end, we want to have a toolbar at the top of any page we load.
Ancak sonunda yklediimiz herhangi bir sayfann st ksmnda bir ara ubuu olmasn istiyoruz.
Therefore we could use the app.js file but the best place of course is our layout.
Bu nedenle evet dosyasn kullanabiliriz, ancak tabii ki en iyi yer bizim dzenimizdir.
This in the end is about laying out our page and this is where we already added some placeholders for the
Disneyland sayfamz dzenlemekle ilgilidir ve burada ara ubuu iin baz
toolbar here.
yer tutucular ekledik.
So in the layout component, let's import the newly created toolbar component from that toolbar file under
Bylece, dzen bileeninde, yeni oluturulmu ara ubuu bileenini, ara ubuu dosyasndaki gezinme ara ubuu
navigation toolbar and then its toolbar.js,
altndan ve ara ubuundan ie aktaralm.
as always without the file extension. And then we can simply replace our placeholder here with these
J. S. her zamanki gibi dosya uzants yoktur ve daha sonra
newly imported toolbar component,
yer tutucumuzu burada yeni alnan ara ubuu bileeniyle deitirebiliriz.
we can use a self-closing component. And now make sure to save all files,
Kendiliinden kapanan bir bileen kullanabilir ve tm dosyalar kaydettiinizden emin olamayz.
make sure npm start is still running and you should see the toolbar like this. Now
UM balatma ileminin hala altndan emin olun ve u an ara ubuunu grmelisiniz.
it's not super pretty,
Sper gzel deil.
the text probably should be white but we're going to replace all these things with some real content
Metin muhtemelen beyaz olmal ama sonra bunlar baz gerek ierikle
later on
deitireceiz.
anyways. One thing we also can notice is that our main page here is overlapped by the toolbar so that
56 piksellik ara ubuunun yksekliine 16 punto Deese eklemeliyiz C dzeni u ekilde hzlca yaplabilir:
main element here which has a margin top of 16px should probably add these 16px to the toolbar
Herneyse hepimiz fark edebileceimiz bir ey, burada ana sayfamzn ara ubuuyla akmasdr; burada ana unsurun
height of 56px which we set up. So we can quickly do that in the layout.css file
16 punto stnde bir kenar boluu var, bu ekilde biz kurduumuz
where I do define this content class which sets the margin top and I want to change this to 72 which
Kenar boluunu belirleyen bu sabit maddeyi bulmak iin nerde buluyorum ve 72'ye deitirmek istiyorum,
essentially is just 56px height of the toolbar plus the 16px height or margin top
esas olarak ara ubuunun sadece 56 piksel yksekliidir Art 16 piksel ykseklik veya kenar boluu st.
actually I wanted to add from before.
Aslnda ben daha nce olmak istedim.
Now if I save this, you see the burger is nicely
imdi visavis kullanm hata ayklayc gzel.
positioned again.
Yine pozisyon.
So with that we add the toolbar, in the next step
Bylece ara ubuunu bir sonraki adma ekledik.
let's work on that logo's so that we get a nice looking logo in this application too.
Bu logo zerinde alalm ki, bu uygulamada gzel bir logo elde edelim.